Guide to the Edward J. Malloy Papers and Photographs TAM.591
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Edward J. Malloy Papers and Photographs
1965-2002
TAM.591
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
1.0 linear feet in one record carton.
Edward J. Malloy (1935-2012) was a labor leader in the Enterprise Association of Steamfitters Local Union 638 United Association and the Building and Construction Trades Council of Greater New York. It contains date books, individual and group photographs of Malloy at events, strikes, and award ceremonies, and other materials.
Malloy, Edward J., 1935-2012
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Arrangement
Files arranged alphabetically.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
This collection was donated in 2005 by Edward J. Malloy. The accession numbers 1950.119, 2005.037 and NPA.2005.042 are associated with this collection.
Scope and Contents note
This collection contains mostly materials generated by Malloy as an executive in the Enterprise Association of Steamfitters Local Union 638 United Association and as the president of the Building and Construction Trades Council of Greater New York, from the late 1980s to 2002. The materials include day planners, diaries, expense files, some correspondence, including thank you notes from Mayor Ed Koch, pamphlets, a masters thesis by Werner Ulrich, certificates of election, badges from conventions, assignments for "Critical Thinking in Human Relations" class, and photographs. The bulk of the collection is made up of individual photographs of Malloy and group portraits of Malloy at events and with individuals including Chuck Schumer, Anthony Weiner, Hillary Clinton, Rudy Guiliani, Elizabeth H. Dole, Archbishop John Joseph O'Connor, Bill Clinton, Edmund J. Bergassi, and others. The photographs also depict building sites and strikes, some personal photographs, golf tournaments, the Boy Scouts of America 1994 Construction Industry "Good Scout Award" ceremony, a protest against New York University's construction site at 201 East 14th Street, Building and Construction Trades Council of Greater New York visit to the New York Stock Exchange, and Malloy as grand marshall of the Saint Patrick's Day Parade in 2001. The collection also contains a program from the Tenth Annual Construction and Building Industry Award Dinner-Dance, where Malloy won an award.
Historical/Biographical Note
Edward J. Malloy (1935-2012) was born and raised in New York City and attended Saint Simon Stock High School in the Bronx. Upon completing his tour of duty with the United States Army in 1957, he was assigned to the 8th Army in Korea. In 1960, he became an apprentice in the Local 638 Steamfitters union. In 1969, Malloy was elected a member of the Trade Board and subsequently a member of the Executive Board. He was appointed Director of the Steamfitting Industry in 1976. In 1979, he was elected Business Agent and in 1983 was elected president of Local 638. He was elected as president of the Building and Construction Trades Council of Greater New York in 1992 and served until 2008. His biggest accomplishment as president was the Project Labor Agreements (PLAs), which promoted measures to contain construction costs and maximize employment opportunities for union members for major public works projects. He also served as a member of the Board of Directors of Empire Blue Cross/Blue Shield, a member of the Board of Directors of the New York Building Congress, a member of the New York State Fire Code Committee, Labor Chairman of the New York Blood Center, and vice president of the New York State AFL-CIO. In 2001, he was selected as Grand Marshal of the New York City St. Patrick’s Day Parade. He died on Tuesday, May 15th, 2012, at age 77.
New York Building Congress.; United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry. Local 638.; Building trades |x Employees |x Labor Unions |z United States.; Building trades |x Employees |z New York (State) |z New York.
- Boy Scouts of America, 1994 Construction Industry "Good Scout Award" Photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Building and Constructions Trades Council of Greater New york at the New York Stock Exchange Photographs, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Building Sites and Strikes Photographs, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Certificates of Election, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- "Critical Thinking in Human Relations," Harry Kelber, Oct 1987 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Diary, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Edmund J. Bergassi Agency, Inc. Surety Bonds Photographs, Includes Group Portraits with Malloy, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Executive Planner, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Executive Planner, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Executive Planner, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Executive Planner, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Expenses, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Expenses, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Group Portraits, 1965-1990 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Group Portraits, circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Group Portraits, Mostly From Labor of Love Golf Tournament, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "How Unions Help Your Family" Pamphlet, "The Decline of Unionism in the Construction Trades," Research Paper by Warner Ulrich, and Thank You Note, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs, circa 1965-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Photographs, Mainly Group Portraits and Meetings, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Photographs of Malloy at Meetings and parades and Professional Group Portraits [1 of 2], 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Photographs of Malloy at Meetings and parades and Professional Group Portraits [2 of 2], 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Saint Patrick's Day Parade Photographs, 2001 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- "Shame on You NYU" Photographs, circa 2001 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Steamfitters Local 638 Badge and Badge and Ribbon from the 33rd Annual Convention United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Tenth Annual Construction and Building Industry Award Dinner-Dance Program, May 18, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Thank You Notes from Edward I Koch and Marvin J Boede, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 27)